door [music]
the West Wing. He escorts us in straight
into the Oval Office.
>> [music]
>> There's the president, the vice
president, the national security
advisor, the CIA director, and then my
boss and me.
>> [music]
>> The president says, "Gentlemen, please
sit." So, we all sit, and I'm looking
around, and I remember [music] saying to
myself,
"My friends would never believe me if I
told them where I was right now.
>> [music]
>> Never believe me."
So, the president says, "Well,
now what do we [music] do?"
And then everybody turns and looks at
me.
And it took [music] me a second, and I
said,
"Oh, um Mr. President, as you know,
[music] Iraqi troops I have chills right
now thinking of it, just remembering it.
I said Iraqi troops crossed the Kuwaiti
border
>> [music]
>> uh at 2:00 in the morning. They seized
the entirety of Kuwait. The royal family
has fled to Saudi Arabia, you know, blah
blah blah blah."
>> [music]
>> And he says,
"Do we know who is in charge in Kuwait
right now?"
>> [music]
>> I said, "Yes, sir, we do. The Iraqis
made an announcement that Dr. Ahmed
Khatib
>> [music]
>> uh is now the occupation governor of
Iraq."
"Do we know anything about him?" I said,
"Yes, sir." I had actually written an
article about him a month earlier just
because he was interesting to me.
I said, "Yes, sir, he's a medical
doctor. He hates the royal family
because his mother was a slave
>> [music]
>> uh in the household of the royal family.
They had slavery until 1955
in the uh on the Arabian Peninsula.
>> [music]
>> So, I said she's a Sudan- she was a
Sudanese slave um to sort of make up for
it. When slavery ended, they [music]
sent Ahmed to the American University of
Beirut. He trained there as a doctor,
>> [music]
>> but his college roommate was George
Habash, and together they founded the
Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine." [music]
And the vice president says, "Jesus
Christ!" Like that.
And the president just goes like this,
and he says, "Gentlemen, [music] thank
you. That'll be Fair
I need to think about this.
Well, later that afternoon, [music]
Margaret Thatcher famously now called
him. He genuinely didn't know what to
do.
>> And you're talking about Papa Bush.
>> Papa Bush.
>> Yeah.
>> [music]
>> And she said, "George, now's not the
time to go wobbly."
Next thing you know, [music]
we have six aircraft carrier battle
groups on on their way to the Gulf,
>> [music]
>> quarter of a million ground troops,
and we liberated Kuwait
>> [music]
>> February 1991.
>> Wow. Wow. And and you played a role in
that at How were you 30 yet?
>> I was 26.
>> And and did you Was there any part of
you that's like, "I shouldn't be here. I
don't really know what I'm saying."
>> Oh, everybody has imposter syndrome. All
of us did. I remember thinking,
you know,
"Why me? Who am I? I'm just some guy
from Pennsylvania.
And here I am sitting with the
president, telling the president what to
do."
But you know what? I
I liked it. I enjoyed it. It was
exciting.
I was on a plane once from
Milan
to Sofia, Bulgaria.
I never talk to people on planes. I
just, you know, put in my earbuds, read
a book, whatever.
>> You did that purposely not to blow your
>> Not to blow my cover.
>> Okay.
>> And there's this guy next to me, this
Italian guy. He's
the whole flight. And and I'm trying to
give him one-word answers. And what they
taught us in training is
they ask you what you do for a living,
just tell them something that's so
boring that they don't ask follow-up
questions.
>> [laughter]
>> Cuz usually I'd say,
"Oh, I'm involved in training. We we
train people, you know, who do
international trade and import-export."
And and people are like, "Oh, that
sounds great." And that's the end of it.
So this guy
Finally I said,
"Okay, look.
I smuggle women and cigarettes from
Eastern Europe. Are you happy now?"
And he goes, "Well,
I don't think I approve." I said, "I
didn't ask your [__] approval."
And then he just kind of sat there like
this the rest of the flight. And I
thought to myself, "Finally.
>> [laughter]
>> At least I didn't blow my cover."
>> Yeah, yeah. Hey guys, I think a bunch of
you know that I'm on a health journey
these days. I'm trying to cook
different, maybe try and exercise a
little bit differently, trying to walk
more, even trying to sleep better. But
even with all that, my favorite cousin
kept pushing me. She said you should
consider supplements. And if I'm honest,
I was a little bit hesitant. I don't
know whether it's because I was busy,
whether I just didn't want more stuff in
my body, but recently I found something
really beautiful. If you haven't tried
Dose before, this is a wonderful
supplement. It's about 2 oz. A lot of
folks say it tastes like mango but with
a little bit of kick in it. It's got
beautiful things like turmeric and
ginger and lemon, all sorts of goodness
in it. And it's great if you've got
cholesterol issues like yours truly, or
even if you're just thinking about kind
of general liver health. Look, I'm no
doctor, but I know that good stuff is
good stuff. And so I hope you'll
consider this. And if you do, tell them
that Carlos sent you. Go ahead and get
35% off. Enjoy it, enjoy it, and enjoy
it. And so you're rising. Are you on
your way to becoming the director of the
CIA?
>> I wish.
>> I mean I mean were you on that
trajectory? Like would Like would
someone reviewing the the rising young
superstars have have tagged you as one
of the rising young superstars?
>> No, that is a very, very political
position. And there have only been
three, I guess, directors over the years
who were career CIA officers. Everybody
else has been an outsider. A former FBI
director, lots of generals, which I
think is always like historically been a
big mistake.
>> And And why would they want generals?
>> I don't know. You get four shiny stars
on your shoulder and they think that
you're Superman, you can do anything.
And it was my experience that
people became four-star generals by
saying, "Yes, sir."
You don't want somebody in that position
to say, "Yes, sir." You want somebody in
that position who can say, "Mr.
President, let me tell you why that's a
terrible idea.
Right? You need somebody with the the
wherewithal to stand up to the policy
makers.
>> So, it's so clear to me that you still
love and revere the work that you did
and that you were one of the fortunate
people in this life who actually got to
do something that they both dreamed of.
>> I thoroughly enjoyed my career.
>> Yeah, you you you enjoyed it.
>> But
after 9/11 everybody went nuts.
They just went nuts. They acted like
the law, whether domestic or or
international, meant nothing to us. We
were the good guys. We had been wronged.
We were going to take revenge.
And you're either with us or you're
against us. And if you're against us,
then get out.
>> I know that torture and the question
around torture ends up becoming a place
where you you you raise your hand and
where you object. And I know that that
ultimately metastasized, but just give
us a version of that for people who
don't know the story.
>> Well, I was one of 14 people asked if I
wanted to be trained in the use of what
they called enhanced interrogation
techniques. I was the only one of the 14
who said no. I believed it was illegal.
Besides being immoral and unethical, I
thought it was illegal. It was illegal.
It was clearly illegal. Any [__] can
read the law that we wrote, the the
Federal Torture Act of 1946. Anybody can
read the the United Nations Convention
Against Torture and Cruel and Inhumane
Treatment.
And
I mean, it it doesn't get any clearer
clearer than that.
>> Take me Take me through torture. So,
you're one of 14 people who they ask
they they ask, "Do you want to get
trained in this?" And you're like, "No,
it's illegal." Take Take me.
>> Yeah.
Buddy of mine in the Counterterrorism
Center who happened to be
a psychiatrist, MD, PhD, and a Brigadier
General in the Army.
And we go to the same church and we're
in the same men's group. He said to me
one day, "Buddy, you know,
you know, they call you the human rights
guy behind your back. And I said, "Yeah,
I know."
And he said, "You know that's not a
compliment, right?"
And I said, "Steve, I'm right and
they're wrong.
And I'm comfortable with my position."
Well,
that was not the popular position to
take.
And so,
they kind of squeezed me out, but I had
done so well in Pakistan that I became
the executive assistant to the Deputy
Director for Operations.
So, um
my career just continued
to go straight up.
>> So, that was a big deal though to raise
your hand on a question of principle.
>> one.
>> And you and your career still keeps
going well?
>> Because I had a rabbi
who
>> My dad My dad always says that My dad
always says, "You don't need a mentor,
you need a rabbi or an angel."
>> That's it.
>> Yeah.
>> He sat above the guys
making these torture decisions.
And he said, "Don't worry about it." And
he said, "You did the right thing." He
called it a slippery slope. He said,
"You know how these guys are. Somebody's
going to kill a prisoner and then
they're going to go to they're going to
go to prison."
>> And what exactly were they doing? Like
I've heard the word waterboarding, but
like for someone who, again, has never
been in the room.
>> Okay, so let's say you are laying on
this slab of of granite right here, but
it's slightly elevated so your feet are
a little bit higher than your than your
head. They'll wrap your your face and
head in material, a towel, you know,
whatever,
tie you down so you can't move,
and then pour water on your face. So,
water gets in your mouth, you start to
drown. W- W- In the case of Abu
Zubaydah, he actually did drown. He was